Soviet Union and Russia Roman Catholic Subject Files, Inclusive: 1930-2003, undated, Bulk: 1971-1988, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union and Russia Roman Catholic Subject Files
Inclusive: 1930-2003, undated, Bulk: 1971-1988, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
28
The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
16 A4 document boxes
The Soviet Union and Russia Roman Catholic Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the history and persecution of the Roman Catholic Church and the life of Catholic Christians in the former Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria, and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
In the late 1960s, Keston began collecting materials on the persecution of Roman Catholics in the Soviet Union.
Oppression of the Roman Catholic Church in Russia and the USSR has a deep history. The divide between East and West occurred long before the first bricks were laid for the Berlin Wall, arguably in 1045 CE with the East-West Schism, or when the divide between the Roman Catholic and Greek Orthodox branches of Christianity became formalized in Europe. In the 16th century, Ivan the Terrible led anti-Catholic campaigns in Russian territories because authorities perceived Catholics as a threat to Eastern Orthodoxy. Anti-Catholic campaigns quieted during the reign of Peter the Great when Russian nobility made efforts to become more “westernized.”
Anti-Catholic sentiment began again in earnest with the 1917 Revolution and formation of the communist state. After the Second World War, Josef Stalin attempted to infiltrate the Catholic Church in other Warsaw Pact countries. Oppression included allowing churches to operate as normal but with state-controlled clergy. Other than these so-called “national churches,” Roman Catholics experienced relatively peaceful lives under Stalin. His successor Nikita Khrushchev saw the Roman Catholic Church as a threat to the sovereignty of the communist state because the Church did not answer to the Soviet leader but rather to the Pope. Thus began a vicious propaganda campaign against Soviet Roman Catholics that utilized their own iconography and leaders. The Catholic Church had been inextricably linked to the West and therefore represented the enemy. Catholic churches in Soviet territory particularly suffered during Khrushchev’s anti-religious campaign.
At the beginning of the 1917 Revolution, more than 500,000 Catholics in Russia professed their faith. At the start of the Second World War, Russia contained approximately 350 Roman Catholic parishes and two dioceses. Estimates suggest that fewer than 140,000 individuals adhere to Roman Catholicism in Russia today. The drastic decrease seems largely due to persecution during the anti-religious campaigns. Even contemporary Roman Catholic priests serving Russian parishes have been stripped of visas and forbidden to preach. The official anti-religious campaigns of Khrushchev during the 20th century thus spill over to the 21st century as many Roman Catholics still feel the pressure of persecution.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union and Russia Roman Catholic Subject Files contain materials on state persecution of the Roman Catholic Church in the Soviet Union and the Catholic fight for human rights. The files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, transcripts, reports, and various forms of Samizdat, including underground publications and unofficially circulated documents and records.
The materials cover a period from 1930 to 2003, with the bulk from 1971 to 1988. The most notable topics include, but are not limited to, Soviet state authority oppressive practices against Roman Catholic believers in Moldavia and Lithuania, the Catholic Committee for the Defense of Believers Rights, and the Lithuanian Memorandum that is considered a founding document of Lithuanian religious independence. Individual accounts of persecution include the trials of Cardinal Vincentas Sladkevicius, Bishops Julionas Stepanavicius and Sigidas Tamkevicius, and priests Fr. Alfonsas Svarinskas and Fr. Juozas Zdebskis in Lithuania; Bishop Boleslavs Sloskans in Latvia; Fr. Matvey Zavalnyuk in Moldavia; Lithuanian Catholics Nijole Sadunaite, Balys Gajauskas, Petras Plumpa, Julius Sasnauskas, Vytautas Skuodis, and Antanas Terleckas; and Latvian Catholic Alexander Riga.
Some materials pertain to relations between the Roman Catholic Church and the state in post-Soviet Russia.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received most of the Soviet Union and Russia Roman Catholic materials in files organized by subject. This original filing system has been largely preserved. Materials pertaining to the Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania have been organized into a separate series.
The Soviet Union and Russia Roman Catholic Subject Files are arranged into three series: I. General, II. Lithuania, and III. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 28.
Related Resources
Related references
Kradonkiewicz, Thaddeus. “The Catholic Church in Russia, Its History, Present Situation and Problems, Perspectives.” Catholic Faith. March-April 1998.
Kishkovsky, Sophia. "Archbishop Appeals To Rights Groups." New York Times. September 13, 2002.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Aušra.; Gajauskas, Balys.; Plumpa, P., 1939-; Riga, Sandr, 1939-; Sadu¯naite:&, Nijole:&.; Sapiets, Janis.; Sapiets, Marite.; Sasnauskas, Julius, 1959-; Skuodis, Vytautas.; Sladkevičius, Vincentas.; Sloska¯ns, Bol̦eslavs, 1893-1981.; Tamkevicius, Sigitas.; Terleckas, Antanas.; Zdebskis, Juozas, 1929-1986.
Subjects (Organizations)
Catholic Church -- Lithuania -- History -- 20th century -- Periodicals.; Catholic Church — Lithuania -- History.
Places
Lithuania -- Church history -- Sources -- Periodicals.; Lithuania — Church history.; Soviet Union -- Church history.
Subjects
Christians -- Soviet Union.; Communism and Christianity -- Soviet Union -- History.; Freedom of religion -- Soviet Union.; Government, Resistance to -- Soviet Union.; Human rights.; Lietuvos Katalikų Bažnyčios kronika.; Persecution -- Lithuania -- History -- 20th century -- Sources -- Periodicals.; Persecution -- Lithuania.; Persecution -- Soviet Union.; Underground Literature -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Publications.; Records (Documents)
- General, 1930-2003, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains information on the history and persecution of the Roman Catholic Church in the Soviet Union, state oppressive practices against Roman Catholic believers and their fight for the right to freedom of consciousness.
  The series is in good condition.
  - Roman Catholic Church. General (1 of 2), 1953-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Roman Catholic Church. General (2 of 2), 1979-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Roman Catholic Church. History. General, 1953-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Roman Catholic Church. History. Soviet Period, 1980-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Individual Roman Catholic Believers (1 of 2), 1966-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Individual Roman Catholic Believers (2 of 2), 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Roman Catholic Church Administration, 1960, 1966, 1973-1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Roman Catholic Church. State. Law, 1960-2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church. General, 1930, 1975-2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers. Harassment and Discrimination, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers. Physical Attacks, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers. Fines, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers. Imprisonment, 1973-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - State Interference in Roman Catholic Church Affairs, 1961, 1976-1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers. Misuse of Psychiatry, 1964, 1975-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers. Attacks in Media, 1962-1983, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. General, 1972-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Central Asia, 1970-1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Latvia, 1960-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Russian Federation, 1966-1975, 1988-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Ukraine, 1966-1981, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Festivals and Anniversaries, 1976-1981, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Services and Rituals, 1977-1979, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Modernization, 1966, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Pilgrimage, 1979, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life. Preaching and Conversions, 1976, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Roman Catholic Church Parish Life, 1977-1980, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Defection from Faith, 1962-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Official Roman Catholic Church Publications, 1967-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Roman Catholic Church Monasticism, 1963, 1988-1989, 1991, 1999, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Clergy and Priesthood. General, 1974, 1978-1980, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Roman Catholic Church Hierarchy, 1966-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Individual Roman Catholic Clergy. General, 1955, 1973-1991, 2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Individual Roman Catholic Clergy. Sloskans, Mons. Boleslavs, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Individual Roman Catholic Clergy. Zavalnyuk, Fr. Matvey, 1977-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Roman Catholic Church. International Contacts. General, 1974-1979, 1990-1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Roman Catholic Church. International Relations. Western Reactions, 1969-1987, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Roman Catholic Church. International Relations. Visits from Foreign Delegations, 1981-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Activities Disapproved by the State, 1977-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Catholic Committee for the Defense of Believer's Rights (1 of 2), 1978-11979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Catholic Committee for the Defense of Believer's Rights (2 of 2), 1980-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Roman Catholic Believers. Emigration on Religious Grounds, 1977, 1979, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Philosophy. Theology. Education. Ethics. General, 1967-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Individual Roman Catholic Theologians. Teilhard de Chardin, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Theological Education, 1969-1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Unity. Schisms. Doctrinal Differences, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Statistics, 1967-1983, 1991, 1997, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Ecumenical Relations with Fellow Believers, 1975-1991, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Ecumenical Relations with Other Denominations, 1973-1984, 1992-2003 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Religion and National Identity, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Involvement in Secular Affairs., 1963, 1975-1979, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Art. Architecture. Music. Literature, 1975-1979, 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Women, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Children and Youth, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Family, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Visual Materials, 1971-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Lithuania, 1943-2002, undated; 2
  The series contains information on the history and persecution of the Roman Catholic Church in Soviet Lithuania, oppressive practices against Catholic believers, and their fight for the right to religious freedom.
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. General (1 of 3), 1970-1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. General (2 of 3), 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. General (3 of 3), 1978-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. History. Soviet Period (1 of 2), 1943-1997, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. History. Soviet Period (2 of 2), 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. General, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Gajauskas, Balys, 1975-1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Petkus, Viktoras, 1977-1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Plumpa, Petras, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Sadunaite, Nijole (1 of 2), 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Sadunaite, Nijole (2 of 2), 1979-1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Sasnauskas, Julius, 1980-1982, 1985, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Skuodis, Vytautas, 1980-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Terleckas, Antanas, 1975-1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Administration, 1973-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. State. Law. General, 1967, 1972-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Roman Catholic Church-State Relations in Lithuania, 1973, 1976-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Roman Catholic Church-State Relations in Lithuania. Legislation, 1969, 1973, 1977-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Opening and Reconsecration of Churches, 1986-1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. General, 1966-1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Harassment of Believers, 1979-1981, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Physical Assault of Believers, 1979-1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Disruption of Meetings, 1978-1982, 1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Fines, 1975-1976, 1979, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Interrogations of Believers, 1977-1983, 1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Trials of Believers (1 of 2), 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Trials of Believers (2 of 2), 1979-1986 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Imprisonments of Believers (1 of 4), 1975-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Imprisonments of Believers (2 of 4), 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Imprisonments of Believers (3 of 4), 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Imprisonments of Believers (4 of 4), 1984-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. State Interference in Church Affairs, 1979-1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Refusal of Registration, 1978-1987, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. State Interference in Parish Life, 1978-1979, 1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. State Interference in Religious Education, 1975, 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Expropriation of Church Buildings, 1979-1982, 1987-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Discrimination in Employment, 1975-1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Discrimination in Education, 1977-1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Abuse of Psychiatry, 1974-1983, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. Attacks in Media, 1971, 1974-1975, 1979-1988 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers in Lithuania. House Searches, 1974-1983, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Life. General, 1966, 1970-1977, 1980, 1987-2002, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Festivals and Anniversaries, 1972, 1977, 1979, 1984-1989, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Holy Places, 1966, 1975-1993, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Parish Life, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Defection from Faith, 1962, 1977, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Official Church Publications, 1979-1980, 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Clergy and Priesthood. General, 1964-1983, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Hierarchy, 1970-1991, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Individual Clergy. General, 1971-1989, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Individual Clergy. Cardinal Vincentas Sladkevicius, 1979-2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Individual Clergy. Bishop Julionas Stepanavicius, 1976-1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Individual Clergy. Bishop Sigidas Tamkevicius, 1979-1984, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Individual Clergy. Fr. Alfonsas Svarinskas, 1978-1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Individual Clergy. Fr. Juozas Zdebskis, 1971-1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Clergy and Priesthood. Statistics, 1963-1966, 1976-1979, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. International Relations. General, 1967, 1971, 1975-1983, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. International Relations. Western Reactions, 1976-1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. International Relations. Visits from Foreign Delegations, 1975-1989 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. General, 1974-1982 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. Protests. Romas Kalanta, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. Defense of Believers Rights, 1979-1988 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. Samizdat (1 of 5), 1972-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. Samizdat (2 of 5), 1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. Samizdat (3 of 5), 1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. Samizdat (4 of 5), 1981-1982, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. Samizdat (5 of 5), 1983-1988, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. Samizdat. Lithuanian Memorandum, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Theological Education., 1965-1983, 1988-1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Statistics, 1979-1980, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Relations with Fellow Believers Abroad. General, 1974-1983, 1987-1989, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Relations with Fellow Believers Abroad. Vatican, 1969, 1976-1993, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Relations with Other Denominations. General, 1971, 1976-1981, 1991, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Religion and National Identity, 1966, 1971-1980, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Involvement in Secular Affairs, 1979, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Art, Architecture, 1975-1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Children and Youth. General, 1963, 1971-1983, 1987, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Roman Catholic Church in Lithuania. Sociology and Family. General, 1979-1981 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Samizdat, 1964-1988, undated; 3
  The series contains unofficially distributed information on persecution of the Roman Catholic Church and oppressive practices against Catholic believers in the Soviet Union. The materials include unofficially circulated documents of the Catholic Committee for the Defense of Believers Rights; trial records; believers testimonials, petitions, and appeals; and Lithuanian Roman Catholic underground publications.
  - Individual Roman Catholic Believers. Albrekht, Vladimir, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Individual Roman Catholic Believers. Gudava, Tengiz, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Individual Roman Catholic Believers. Riga, Alexander (Sandr), 1984, 1987, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Return of Church Property, ca. 1979 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers. General, 1978-1985 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Roman Catholic Believers. Harassment, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 11)